Guide to the Hawthorne Family Papers, ca. 1800-1926
Department of Special Collections
Hawthorne Family Papers,
ca. 1800-1926
Special Collections M0981
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1998.
Biography
Sophia A. Hawthorne [1809 - 1871]:
Sophia Amelia Peabody was born in Salem, Massachusetts, on September 21, 1809 to Elizabeth Palmer Peabody and Nathaniel Peabody. She attended a school run by her mother and sister in Salem, Massachusetts and taught there for a short time. In December of 1833, Sophia and her sister Mary traveled to Cuba where, it was hoped, the climate would improve Sophia's delicate health. Her letters home were collected and circulated among friends by her mother as Sophia's "Cuba Journal." After returning to Salem in 1835, Sophia, though still infirm, achieved a reputation as a copyist of artworks. Nathaniel Hawthorne (1804-1864), a neighbor of the Peabodys in Salem, met Sophia late in 1838; it was, Sophia would later say, love at first sight. A long engagement followed, kept secret for some time in the hope that the families would believe Sophia strong enough to marry, and while Nathaniel sought to establish himself as a writer. It had been expected that Sophia would never marry, but her days as an invalid ended on July 9, 1842, their wedding day. As long as Nathaniel was alive, Sophia was strong and vigorous; only after his death did her health begin gradually to fail. The Hawthornes began their married life in the Old Manse, in Concord. Three children came of the profoundly happy marriage: Una in 1844, Julian in 1846, and Rose in 1851. In 1852, Hawthorne was appointed U.S. Consul to England and the family moved to Liverpool. After the completion of his term of office, they traveled about Europe, returning to Concord in 1860, where they remained until Hawthorne's death in 1864. In the seven years after Hawthorne's death, Sophia edited his journals and published them as Passages from the American Notebooks (1868), Passages from the English Notebooks (1870), and Passages from the French and Italian Notebooks (1871). Her own travel writings appeared in 1870, as Notes in England and Italy. Sophia lived her last two years in London, where she died in 1871.
Rose Hawthorne Lathrop [1851 - 1926]:
Born in Lenox, Massachusetts, on May 20, 1851, Rose Hawthorne spent much of her childhood with her family in England and Europe. In 1871, she married George Parsons Lathrop, an aspiring author and editor. A hasty, youthful marriage, it was never a happy one. The Lathrop's one child, Francis, died young, and the couple separated in 1895. Lathrop died in 1898. Rose Hawthorne Lathrop's first published work was a book of poems, Along the Shore (1888); in 1897 her Memories of Hawthorne appeared, following its serial publication in The Atlantic Monthly. Having converted to Roman Catholicism in 1891, Rose Hawthorne Lathrop founded the Servants of Relief for Incurable Cancer after her marriage dissolved. Known as Sister Alphonsa, she and her small religious community nursed the poorest terminally ill cancer patients in New York City. In 1899, the Servants of Relief became a Dominican Congregation and were able to open Rosary Hill Home in 1901. Rose Hawthorne, now Mother Alphonsa, lived and worked there until her death on July 9,1926, her parents' wedding anniversary. Rosary Hill Home continues today as it did almost a century ago: only those patients who are terminally ill and destitute are admitted for care by the Sisters.
Julian Hawthorne [1846-1934]:
Nathaniel's and Sophia's second child and only son, Julian was educated at home and then piecemeal in Concord and Europe. He attended Harvard for three years, finishing training as an engineer in Europe after his father died. He went on to become a prolific and popular writer of short stories, novels, essays, and memoirs. Although he felt encumbered always by his father's accomplishments and reputation, he, like his sisters, was determined to keep his parents' memories alive. In 1884, he published Nathaniel Hawthorne and His Wife and, in 1903, Hawthorne and His Circle. With a certain feckless naïveté, he involved himself in a get-rich-quick scheme that resulted in a conviction for mail fraud and a year's incarceration. Freed in 1913, Julian continued his writing career almost until his death in California in 1936.
Anna Cora (Ogden) Mowatt [1819-1870]:
Author of verse and romantic novels, playwright, and actress, Mowatt had a colorful and successful acting career in New York, retiring to England after the publication of her Autobiography of an Actress in 1854.
Scope and Content
The Hawthorne Family papers at Stanford consist of letters, manuscripts, journals, sketch books, and memorabilia of Sophia Peabody Hawthorne, wife of Nathaniel Hawthorne, and of two of their children, son Julian [1846-1934] and younger daughter, Rose [1851-1926], both writers themselves. The large majority of the papers are from the 1830s to the 1860s; from the last years of the 19th century; and from 1913 through the 1920s. The mid-nineteenth-century papers are for the most part those of Sophia Peabody Hawthorne, her family and circle of friends. Rose Hawthorne Lathrop's holograph manuscripts were written before 1900, and from early in the twentieth century are letters and writings of Julian Hawthorne and letters from Rose Hawthorne Lathrop, who was by then known as Mother Alphonsa. Also included are ca. 54 leaves of holograph notes and verse, and some print material, of Anna Cora Mowatt, undated but probably from the 1850s.
Access Terms
Alcott, Amos Bronson, 1799-1888; Allston, Washington, 1779-1843; Bartlett, Josiah; Blodget, Mrs.; Bridge, Horatio, 1806-1893; Bright, Henry Arthur 1830-1884; Burchmore, H.L.; Burney, Susan; Channing, Ellen Fuller; Channing, William Ellery, 1780-1842; Channing, William Ellery, 1818-1901; Chorley, Henry Fothergill, 1808-1872; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888; Clarke, Sarah; Emerson, Charles, d. 1836; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881; Foote, Mary; Fuller, Sarah Margaret, 1810-1850; Hall, Anna Maria Fielding, 1800-1881; Hall, Samuel Carter, 1800-1889; Hawthorne, Elizabeth Manning; Hawthorne, Maria Louisa, 1807-1852; Hawthorne, Una, 1844-1877; Hedge, Frederic Henry, 1805-1890; Hillard, George Stillman, 1808-1879; Hillard, Susan Tracy Howe; Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1798-1870; Hoar, Elizabeth; Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood, 1816-1895; Hooper, Ellen Sturgis; Hosmer, Harriet Goodhue, 1830-1908; Kemble, Frances Anne (Fanny), 1809-1893; Lathrop, George Parsons, 1851-1898; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891; Lowell, Maria White, d. 1853; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Mann, Mary Tyler Peabody, 1806-1887; Martineau, Basil; Martineau, Edith; Melville, Herman, 1819-1891; Palmer, George; Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, 1778-1853; Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, 1804-1894; Peabody, George Francis, 1813-1839; Peabody, Nathaniel, 1774-1853; Peabody, Nathaniel Cranch, 1811-; Peabody, Wellington, 1815-1837; Pike, William B.; Putnam, Frederic Ward, 1839-1915; Rodman, Benjamin; Shaw, Anna; Shaw, Sarah B.; Smyth, Hildegard; Sturgis, Mary L.; Tappan, Caroline Sturgis; Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862; Ticknor, William Davis, 1810-1864; Very, Jones, 1813-1880; Weld, Theodore D., 1803-1895; Weston, Emma; Yates, the Misses
Container List
- Series 1: Correspondence relating to Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne [1809-1871]
  - To Elizabeth Palmer Peabody [1778-1853], ca.1843-1852 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Item 1. AL fragment, [ca. 1843]., 1 leaf.
    - Item 2. AL, initials, 1844 March 16., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 3. ALS, 1844 Nov. 19., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 4. AL fragment, 1845 Dec. 7., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 5. AL fragment, 1846 [Feb. 22]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 6. AL, initial, fragment, [1849 February]., 1 leaf.
    - Item 7. AL fragment, [1852?, Summer]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 8. ALS, 1852 July 4., 2 folded leaves.
    - Item 9. ALS, 1852 Aug. 13., 3 folded leaves.
    - Item 10. AL, 1852 Sept. 19., 2 folded leaves + 1 leaf.
    - Item 11. ALS fragment, [ca. 1852 Oct.]., 1 leaf.
    - Item 12. ALS, 1851 [i.e., 1852] Oct. 24., 2 folded leaves.
  - To Elizabeth Palmer Peabody [1804-1894], early 1830s-1839 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Item 1. ALS fragment, [early 1830s]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 2. ALS, [1830s?]., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. ALS, [1836]., 1 leaf
    - Item 4. ALS, [1837] May 19., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 5. AL, initials, [ca. 1838]., 1 leaf
    - Item 6. ALS fragment, [1838]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 7. ALS, [1838?] Feb., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 8. ALS, [1838?]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 9. AL fragment [to EPP (sister)?], [1838?]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 10. ALS, 1839 June 28., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 11. ALS, 1839 June 29., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 12. AL, 1839 July., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 13. ALS, 1839 July 27., 1 folded leaf.
  - From Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, ca. 1832-1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Item 1. To Mary Peabody: ALS, [ca. 1832]., 1 folded leaf, partly excised.
    - Item 2. To Mary Foote: ALS, 1842 July 5., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 3. To Mary Foote: ALS, 1842 Dec. 18., 2 folded leaves.
    - Item 4. To Mary Foote: AL, initials, 1843 April 6., 3 folded leaves, 1 partly excised.
    - Item 5. To Mary Foote: ALS, 1843 August 11., 2 folded leaves.
    - Item 6. To Mary Foote: ALS, 1843 Oct. 15., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 7. To Mary Foote: ALS, 1845 May 4., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 8. To [unknown]: AL fragment, [ca. 1851]., 1 folded leaf + scrap.
    - Item 9. Autograph fragment, [1858 Summer]., 1 leaf [Was enclosed with Rose Hawthorne Lathrop ALS, 1925 June 3. The ALS is filed at Box 2, Folder 5, Item 1.]
  - To Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne from her sisters, 1833-ca.1858 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Item 1. From Mary Peabody: AL fragment, 1833 June 19., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 2. From Elizabeth Palmer Peabody: ALS, [1838]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 3. From Elizabeth Palmer Peabody: AL, initial, [1839] June 28., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 4. From Elizabeth Palmer Peabody: ALS, [ca. 1858] April 25., 1 leaf
  - To Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, 1825-1837 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Item 1. From George Palmer: ALS, 1825 Nov. 11., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 2. From [unknown]: ALS, 1826 Jan. 19., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 3. From Benjamin Rodman: ALS, 1831 April 17., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 4. From [Sarah Clarke?]: AL, [ca. mid-1830s]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 5. From Sarah [Clarke?]: ALS, [ca. mid-1830s]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 6. From H. L. Burchmore: ALS, 1835 July 25., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 7. From Frederic H. Hedge: ANS, 1837 Sept. 4., 1 folded leaf.
  - To Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, 1841-1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Item 1. From R. Waldo Emerson: ALS, 1841 April 20., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 2. From Mary L. Sturgis: ALS, [1841] Nov. 24., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. From Maria [White Lowell]: ALS, [ca. early 1842]., 1 leaf
    - Item 4. From Maria White [Lowell]: ALS, 1842 March 31., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 5., 6. A Message from the Garden: two copies of poem in 2 unknown hands, 1842 July 3. Each copy, 1 leaf
    - Item 7. Poem fragment, [in unknown hand, dated 1841]., 1 leaf [Vermin damage obliterates some text.]
    - Item 8. From Maria [White Lowell]: ALS, 1844 March 21., 1 folded leaf.
  - To Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, ca.1842-1867[?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Item 1. Ellen [Hooper]: ALS, [ca. 1842]., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 2. Sarah [B. Shaw]: ALS, [ca. 1844]., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. S[arah] B S[haw]: AL, initials, [1846?] Oct. 10., 1 leaf
    - Item 4. H[oratio] Bridge: ALS, 1845 June 21., 1 folded leaf [loss of corner ca. 3 X 4 affects text].
    - Item 5. E[lizabeth] Hoar: ALS, 1846 Feb. 20., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 6. E[lizabeth] Hoar: ALS, 1848 May 24., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 7. Emma Weston: ALS, [ca. 1858?], 1 leaf
    - Item 8. Theodore D. Weld: ALS, 1866 Dec. 31., 1 leaf
    - Item 9. E[than] A[llen] Hitchcock: ALS, 186[7?] March 24., 1 leaf & cvr.
  - To Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Item 1. Photograph of a letter from Herman Melville, ALS, 1852 Jan. 8. [Location of original unknown.], [Vermin damage affects text.]
  - To Nathaniel Hawthorne [1804-1864] & to Sophia A. Hawthorne, 1850-1856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Item 1. To NH from Geo[rge] S. Hillard: ALS, 1850 March 28., 1 folded leaf [re: Scarlet Letter], with a) Original cover addressed to Nathaniel Hawthorne, with, in Nathaniel Hawthornes hand: Geo. S. Hillard; the Scarlet Letter b) cover, with note in Rose Hawthorne Lathrop s hand re: above items
    - Item 2. To Nathaniel Hawthorne from Wm. B. Pike: ALS, 1852 July 18., 1 folded leaf.
    - Item 3. To Sophia A. Hawthorne from A[nna] M. Hall: ALS, [1856]., 1 leaf
    - Item 4. To Sophia A. Hawthorne from A[nna] M. Hall: ALS, [1856]., 2 leaves.
    - Item 5. To Sophia A. Hawthorne from A[nna] M. Hall: AL, [1856]., 1 leaf
    - Item 6. To Sophia A. Hawthorne from A[nna] M. Hall, ALS [1856]., 1 leaf
    - Item 7. To Nathaniel Hawthorne from S[amuel] C[arter] Hall: ALS, [1856] Aug. 9., 1 leaf & cvr.
- Series 2: Journals and Verse of Sophia A. Hawthorne
  - Journals, 1832-1833 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Item 1. Autograph journal, 1832 Oct. 22-1832 Nov. 22. 33 pp.
    - Item 2. Autograph journal, [1833 Feb.] 3-[1833] March 5. 18 pp.
  - Cuba Journal, 1833-1834 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Item 1. [1833] Dec. 20 - 1834 June 2., 101 leaves in an unknown hand.
  - Cuba Journal, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Item 1. [1834] June 5 - [1834] July 4., 98 leaves in an unknown hand.
  - Journals, ca.1849-1853 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Item 1. Autograph fragments, [ca.1849]. 24 pieces, 1 dated: 1849 July 29.
    - Item 2. Autograph journal, 1853 April 14 - [1853] May 2., 18 leaves.
  - Manuscript verse, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Item 1. To the Unknown yet known; The Human Form: 2 autograph poems, [n.d.]., 1 folded leaf.
- Series 3: Sketchbooks of Sophia A. Hawthorne & Rose Hawthorne [1851-1926], ca. 1834-ca.1861
  - Sketchbook, n.d. (a portion is not after 1839) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, Rose Hawthorne., 1 v. (ca. 27 leaves, incl. glassine).
  - Sketchbook, ca.1834-ca.1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Sophia Amelia Peabody, in Cuba; Rose Hawthorne (age 10)., 1 v. (ca. 40 leaves).
- Series 4: Correspondence relating to Rose Hawthorne Lathrop [1851-1926]
  - From Mother Mary Alphonsa (Rose Hawthorne Lathrop), 1913-1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Item 1. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1913 April 6., 4 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 2. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1913 June 4., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 3. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1913 July 20., 3 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 4. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1914 Feb. 14, to Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1914 Feb. 14.; 1 leaf;; 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 5. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1914 March 28., 1 leaf
    - Item 6. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1914 Nov. 25., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth and Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1915 Jan. 10., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 8. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1915 Feb. 28., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 9. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1917 Feb. 18., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 10. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1917 June 3., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 11. To Clifford Smyth: ACS, 1917 June 15.
  - From Mother Mary Alphonsa (Rose Hawthorne Lathrop), 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Item 1. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1918 March 22., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 2. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1918 March 26., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1918 April 10., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 4. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1918 April 25., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 5. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1918 May 5., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 6. Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 Jan. 15, 1 leaf; encl.: ANS 1919 Jan. 14, Carrie Bolze to Mother Alphonsa.
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 April 7., 3 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 8. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 May 5, 1 folded leaf & cvr.; newsprint clipping: an appeal for St. Roses free Home & Rosary Hill Home, [n.d.].
    - Item 9. To Clifford Smyth and Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1919 May 19., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 10. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 Nov. 12., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 11. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 Nov. 23, 1 leaf & cvr.; Rose Hawthorne Lathrop poem; printed clipping [n.d.].
    - Item 12. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1919 Nov. 30, 2 leaves & cvr.; 2 prayer cards.
  - From Mother Mary Alphonsa (Rose Hawthorne Lathrop), 1920-1923 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Item 1. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1920 Jan. 1., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 2. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1921 Jan. 30., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 April 6., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 4. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 May 25., 1 leaf, note, & cvr.
    - Item 5. To New York Times Advertising Manager: ANS, 1922 May 25, autograph testimonials, Rose Hawthorne Lathrop, [n.d.].; 1 leaf & cvr.;; 2 leaves.
    - Item 6. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 May 26., 5 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 July 17., 5 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 8. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 Sept. 10., 2 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 9. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1922 Oct. 13., 2 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 10. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1923 Feb. 26. 3 leaves & cvr.; to Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1923 Feb. 26., 1 leaf
    - Item 11. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1923 March 1, to Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, [1923?] March 2; Catholic News acknowledgment card, clipping pasted to verso, [n.d.].; 1 leaf & cvr.;; 1 leaf;
    - Item 12. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1923 Oct. 8., 1 leaf & cvr.
  - From Mother Mary Alphonsa (Rose Hawthorne Lathrop), 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Item 1. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth & Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1924 Jan. 8., 2 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 2. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1924 Oct. 27, 1 leaf & cvr.; card, ms notes, [n.d.]
    - Item 3. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1924 Oct. 29., 2 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 4. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1924 Nov. 18, 1 leaf & cvr.; photograph: Rosary Hill Home, Hawthorne, New York,[n.d.].
    - Item 5. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 Jan. 14., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 6. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 Jan. 27., 1 leaf & cvr. [Vermin damage affects text.]
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 Feb. 4., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 8. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 April 6., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 9. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 April 28., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 10. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: ALS, 1925 April 28., 1 leaf & cvr.
  - From Mother Mary Alphonsa (Rose Hawthorne Lathrop), 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Item 1. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 June 3., 3 leaves.
      [Encloses Sophia A. Hawthorne autograph notes fragment from Summer 1858, re: seance. The fragment is filed at Box 1, Folder 3, Item 9.]
    - Item 2. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 June 10., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 3. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 July 2., 1 laves & cvr.
    - Item 4. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 July 6., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 5. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 July 30, 1 leaf & cvr.; newspaper clipping, [n.d.].
    - Item 6. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1925 Nov. 22., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1926 Jan. 10., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 8. To Clifford Smyth: ALS, 1926 Jan. 31., 2 leaves & cvr.
  - From Sr./Mother Mary Rose [re: Mother Alphonsa], 1926-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Item 1. ALS, 1926 Aug. 13., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 2. ALS, 1926 Oct. 26., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 3. ALS, 1926 Dec. 14., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 4. ALS, 1927 April 10., 1 leaf, note, & cvr.; Easter greeting card; prayer card.
    - Item 5. ALS, 1927 May 24., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 6. ALS, 1929 Aug. 6., 1 leaf & cvr.
- Series 5: Rose Hawthorne Lathrop Verse, Notes, & Prose
  - Manuscript verse (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Item 1. Psychical Research: autograph poem signed., 4 leaves.
    - Item 2. Never, Again!: autograph poem signed., 3 leaves.
    - Item 3. A Yachting Goodbye: AMsS, 2 copies. 8 leaves.
    - Item 4. Home Again!: AMs, initialed:, 5 leaves & notebook leaf with ms notes.
    - Item 5. Several poems, fragments, & notes, some signed, one initialed., 13 leaves.
    - Item 6. Several poems, some initialed or signed., 8 leaves.
    - Item 7. Several poems, some signed., 10 leaves.
    - Item 8.Several poems, some signed., 20 leaves.
  - Rose Hawthorne Lathrop, AMsS, 6 fragments in 72 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rose Hawthorne Lathrop, AMs, 5 fragments in 76 leaves; newsclipping. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fragments of Rose Hawthorne Lathrops ms. of Memories of Hawthorne (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Item 1. Draft of chapter headings for memoir of Hawthorne family, [n.d.]., 6 leaves.
    - Item 2. Fragment from journal of Sophia A. Hawthorne, [n.d.]., 72 leaves.
    - Item 3. Letter fragment in Rose Hawthorne Lathrop s hand, [n.d.]., 1 leaf [Sophia A. Hawthorne to (unknown), ca. 1854].
    - Item 4. Letter[?] fragment in Rose Hawthorne Lathrops[?] hand, [n.d.]., 1 leaf torn in two. [Sophia A. Hawthorne to Nathaniel Hawthorne from Lisbon(?), ca. 1855-1856 Winter].
    - Item 5. Fragment of draft of memoir of Hawthorne family.
  - Editing of Sophia A. Hawthorne's Madeira journal, In Rose Hawthorne Lathrops & unknown hands, [n.d.]. 63 leaves of 113, numbered 659-721. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Editing of Sophia A. Hawthorne's Madeira journal, In unknown hand corrected by Rose Hawthorne Lathrop, 50 leaves of 113, numbered 722-771. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Autograph notebook/copybook, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Autograph journal, signed, [begins] 1873 June 17, notes laid in. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 3 autograph notebooks, 1 initialed, [n.d.] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bucephalus the Great: AMsS, [n.d.], 42 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Daring Hill: AMs notebook, [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Love is the Theme: AMsS, [n.d.]., 90 leaves [wants leaves numbered 12, 13]. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A Story of the Heart: AMs, initialed, [n.d.]., 18 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - At the Beach: AMsS, [n.d.]., 14 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Haunted Road: AMsS, [n.d.]., 10 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Desperate Voyage: AMs, [n.d.]., 169 leaves [chapters 1-7]. [Leaf 9 misnumbered 10.] (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - A Desperate Voyage: AMsS, [n.d.]., 84 leaves [Ch. 8-end (2 chapters are labeled 8)]. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cherry Burton: AMs, [n.d.]., 1 AN + 23 leaves [2 chapters]. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Woman, [The American Lady], n.d., 1 magazine leaf. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series 6: Julian Hawthorne [1846-1934]: Correspondence and Miscellany
  - Correspondence, 1852-1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Item 1. To Elizabeth Palmer Peabody [1804-1894]: ALS, 1852 Feb. 28., 1 leaf
    - Item 2. To Elizabeth Palmer Peabody [1804-1894]: ALS, 1852 March 29., 1 leaf
    - Item 3. To Nathaniel Peabody [1774-1855]: ALS, 1853 [early]., 1 leaf
    - Item 4. To Wm. Reick: TLS, 1904 Nov. 30., 1 leaf
    - Item 5. To Beatrix Hawthorne Smyth: TLS, [n.d.]., 1 leaf
    - Item 6. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, [n.d.]., 1 leaf
    - Item 7. To Clifford Smyth: TL, initials, 1912 April 8., 1 leaf
    - Item 8. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1914 Dec. 23., 1 leaf
    - Item 9. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1919 July 9., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 10. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1919 July 17., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 11. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1919 Dec. 3., 2 leaves.
    - Item 12. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1919 Dec. 22., 2 leaves & cvr.
    - Item 13. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1922 March 5., 1 leaf
    - Item 14. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1924 Nov. 9., 1 leaf
    - Item 15. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1924 Dec. 7., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 16. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1924 Dec. 24., 1 leaf
    - Item 17. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1925 Jan. 28., 1 leaf & cvr.
    - Item 18. To Clifford Smyth: TLS, 1925 March 14., 1 leaf & cvr.